A little while back, I covered the
sprint study, which unlike the name, has
nothing to do with running, but a lot to
do with blood pressure. Essentially, it
was a highly influential study from back
in 2015 that made us readjust our blood
pressure recommendations for reducing
cardiovascular risk. However, soon after
that analysis released, I was flooded
with comments telling me the study was
garbage. And that another analysis, a
far bigger analysis by the esteemed
Cochran Review indicates the sprint
study is wrong. And then I realized
where these comments are coming from. A
recent video by the low carb espousing
internal medicine physician Dr. Bos with
a powerful title, the great high blood
pressure scam came and slapped me across
the face. I mean figuratively, of
course. So, why don't we see if this has
any merit and what this is all about by
hearing Dr. Bos's interpretation of the
data and then adding some what I think
is much needed context. As an FYI, Dr.
Bos did a lengthy deep dive which will
be uh linked, but since the video is
really long, I've sped up her parts so
that we can uh get through it more
quickly and I don't like talking quickly
as is already apparent. So, first let's
get to a bit of context on the issue at
hand. Uh, so this is this uh this review
that came out in 2022. Um, and it is
looking at blood pressure targets for
treatment of people with hypertension
and cardiovascular disease. All right, I
want to skip down and review uh a couple
of things that I do not want people to
miss. Um, number one is um it's not an
accident that I have a have a video out
there that a million and a half people
have looked at. High blood pressure is
the most preventable cause of premature
death and morbidity meaning making your
life less lovely. Uh high blood
pressure, hypertension is the leading
risk factor for the global burden of
disease. It is a major risk factor for
stroke, heart attack, heart failure,
chronic. I'm not arguing that. Nobody's
arguing that. What the question we're
asking is how how low should we push it.
Right? So as Dr. Bos pointed out, we
know high blood pressure is a major
problem in many cases of heart disease.
But the question is what is considered
high? That part I don't want anybody
writing into my channel saying Dr. Bos
said that I should stop taking my blood
pressure medicine because it doesn't
matter. That is not what I'm saying. I
am saying how low should we treat it to
and and why. So, we're going to go down
to um this this is the objective that
this this group of smarty pants at the
Cochran Library says. We want to know if
uh uh lower blood pressure targets of
systolic and diastolic that less than
135 less than 85 are associated with
reduction in mortality or and morbidity
as compared to the standards which was
this 140 over 140 to 160 over 90 to 100.
Again, that's a range because of the
years of the changing rules um from the
treatment of people with high blood
pressure and a history of cardiovascular
disease, stroke. All right. Of course,
what's in the back of my mind is how I
to a a million and a half people used
the sprint trial to explain that
lowering their blood pressure was going
to save their life. And the question is,
well, was I wrong? Completely agree. I
think all at least a majority of health
practitioners and researchers would
argue high blood pressure is a major
risk factor for heart disease. Then the
question in relation to the sprint trial
which indicated that keeping your blood
pressure if you have cardiovascular
disease below 120 over 80 is superior to
keeping it below 140 over 90. Those are
systolic and diastolic numbers that you
get tested at your doctor's office for
example. However, the Cochran Review the
gold standard for scientific evidence
includes six more randomized control
trials in addition to the sprint trial.
And what did they find? Some results
that might indicate this is all a scam.
Ooh, how juicy, how
tantalizing, how ever so
clandestine. Well, let's uncover the
scam.
First of all, I like to point out that
the the potential biases, and again,
this is fun to see. uh not fun to see.
It's just is what should be in every
trial, but humans are human, right? Uh
they do things that aren't exactly what
we wish they would reveal to us. All
right. So, the biases, there's several
places where they said, "Yeah, these
people had biases. These people had
biases." But these other ones are what I
thought was very interesting. Some of
the
um some of these had a pharmaceutical
industry bias. That's the the hot trial
and the AASK trial. And then this is a
very other curious one where there's
early termination meaning they they
thought the results were so profound
that they didn't finish the study and it
causes a bias. There's a this is again
important because that's the trial that
I was quoting you on. Right. I do think
it's important to look at the bias
assessments performed in these analyses.
They tell us a lot. However, they don't
tell us what Dr. Bos explained. A bias
assessment like a Jad scale or a ROB 2
are standardized checklists researchers
use to assess the potential for bias
that doesn't inform on the actual bias
of the study or the people involved in
the study directly but the potential for
bias to be a factor. So like Dr. Boss
pointed out two of the studies were
funded by the pharmaceutical industry.
So the meta analysis will upgrade those
studies to some potential bias instead
of low risk of bias. On the other hand,
all the studies in this analysis had
some bias because none of them were
placeboc controlled because it's
generally unethical to not help people
with cardiovascular disease just for a
study. So the comparator in this
analysis and all the studies included
was a standard blood pressure treatment
to keep blood pressure below between 160
and 140 systolic and the intensive blood
pressure treatment group kept the
systolic blood pressure under 135. They
used drugs to achieve that and therefore
no placebo. Finally, in relation to why
the sprint study was stopped early,
that's true. It was again an ethics
board that the researchers have to work
with will sometimes call for a study to
end early because the effect is obvious
and keeping people on a standard
treatment might be unethical or the
results are obvious and the trend of the
data has been consistent for a few years
within the trial. So continuing it just
doesn't add any more value to the
interpretation. In fact, stopping a
study early for those reasons, yes, is a
bias because it includes a decision to
stop collecting data before the
predetermined endpoint. But it is a good
thing in this context because the effect
is so profound. Okay, so let's go a
little bit further and we're going to
look at um we're going to look at
relative risk and that's where it leads
me to the next slide. I'm going to
gracefully change slides. There we go.
Oops, not to the Fouchy one again. We're
going to go to the next one and the next
one. All right. A few months ago, I
think it was last summer, I used this
slide to talk about breast cancer and
relative risk. We said yes, the people
that had were in the control, uh, those
had 30 cases of breast cancer in the
control group, those were the people who
didn't take the estrogen. And there were
38 people who were taking hormones and
they got breast cancer. Both groups got
breast cancer, but boy, there were more
breast cancers in the HRT in the PE in
the women who were taking that estrogen.
And it was a big scare and they they
stopped the trial and they said, "Yes,
it's a 26% increase in risk. you've got
to stop taking the breast cancer and you
got to stop taking the estrogen because
of breast cancer in these women. And
they were playing a dirty trick and this
is going to be really important when you
look at some of the numbers I'm about to
go through. They were talking about a
relative risk that sounds harmless. Uh
like, oh, it's a risk, right? And it's
26%. I don't want to increase my breast
cancer by 26%. But that's not that's not
an absolute risk because when you look
carefully these numbers were 30 in
10,000 of the women not taking estrogen
got breast cancer and 38 in 10,000 were
taking estrogen and got breast cancer
and that is an absolute risk and it
shows you that a 0.08% increase is the
risk that that woman was undertaking.
Okay, a lot here. This is a concept
that's often misrepresented and I
definitely wouldn't want to call it a
dirty trick. Although it could be used
nefariously. In fact, I'd argue many
people in the health influencer world
use the opposite argument. Absolute risk
hyperfixation a bit, let's say not
accurately to put it mildly. Okay. So,
what's going on here? One, Dr. Dr. Bos
is explaining relative risk because the
results are reported as relative risk as
they often are in riskbased studies. Her
explanation of the numbers is spot-on.
You can see a 30% increase in risk and
generally they're discussing relative
risk. So it's relative to the other
group. In this case there's more or less
risk of dropping blood pressure below
135 systolic than keeping it above 140.
So in a given scenario, a 30% increase
risk seems scary. But when we look at
the absolute risk, as Dr. Bos correctly
pointed out, the absolute risk is much
smaller because you're no longer simply
comparing against the other group, but
taking into account the number of people
in the study, and the absolute risk is
often very small. Now, if we stopped
there and we'd walk away thinking that
absolute risk is all that matters and
that if absolute risk is something like
0.1% increase risk, I think I'll just
ignore this all. But that would be a
mistake and here's why. Absolute risk
might be tiny initially, but keep in
mind that absolute risk is also
constrained by time. So if the study
runs for three years, the absolute risk
might be tiny, but the absolute risk
tends to increase as time passes. So
that tiny number begins to balloon into
a life-threatening one. Unfortunately,
randomized control trials can't be
effectively done for 30 years. So we
look at a snapshot risk at the trials
end, the relative risk. No doubt it's
good to have both including number
needed to treat or N&T a topic for
another time. But you can see that if
you stop the explanation at absolute
risk is a tiny number so you don't need
to worry about it is misinforming on an
incredibly important aspect of study
analysis to understand. Unfortunately, I
see this often in certain circles. I'll
likely make a video explaining this
concept in more detail. Stay tuned for
that. Anyway, let's move on and show
you. Here's the relative risk for um
well, that's serious adverse respect.
Let's go to this one. This one says
total mortality. See that? Okay. So,
here's the total mortality of all of
these trials that those Cochran uh folks
were looking at and they've got, you
know, one one two three four five six
seven trials that they looked at and
they're looking at just lowering um the
to get to the lower target. That's that
less than 135 over less than 80. And
then they compared them to the old
old-timers, the you know 140 to 160 over
90 to 100. And they're looking at well
what are the what's the total deaths?
This is hard to screw up people. You
shouldn't have a tough time figuring
this one out, right? And you look at
this relative risk. Um by the time you
add up all of these trials, meaning they
were very similar. Uh the larger the
number of the study, the better we can
be confident in it. And you get to the
bottom and you say, "Huh, so if we
criss-cross that one and you move the
decimal point two points, we're at a,
you know, 5% relative risk. pretty tiny
actually and especially when you realize
it's not an absolute risk, it's a
relative risk. So they're trying to show
the noise trying to show is there real
data here. Is there really something and
when you look at you know hazards ratio
relative risk anytime it crosses the one
you should be like we we're not going to
be very confident in this data. I mean
we're not going to be like you should be
worried that they don't have a really
good signal from this information that
they're kind of guessing. Yeah. So I
would describe things slightly
differently but I agree with Dr. Boss.
One, total mortality is a great outcome
because unless we're in Salem's lot,
dead people don't come back to life,
which means that we can count pretty
easily. However, if the data pass the
middle line, that doesn't really speak
to the certainty or the confidence in
the data. There's other tells for that,
like the actual confidence intervals
themselves, but it does tell us there's
likely no effect of dropping blood
pressure to that lower level, that 135
over 85. Yeah, here's uh total
cardiovascular events. We're going to
get to the data here in a second, but 14
fewer cardiovascular events per 100,000
in the lower blood pressure targeted
group. uh the results showed that 565
out of the 55 5300 um in the lower
targeted groups versus the 535. So
again, it's it's a really big math
equation which is why we rely on things
like uh that um hazards ratio or or
relative risk. Um let me go to the next
one down because I again go through the
numbers here looking this this one says
it's a 08 for the lower group and a one
for the regular group. Uh is there a
difference? That is the cardiovascular
mortality I think is that right? Yeah.
No, this is cardiovascular. Did they
have a heart attack? Did they have a
stroke? Um, I just want to chime in for
a second and mention that was 14 out of
1,000, not 10,000. An understandable
misspeak. Just important to distinguish
because that's a huge difference.
Anyway, let's let Dr. Bos finish her
main point here. Here's for those of you
that are just trying to say, "What's the
punch line?" And please don't give up on
me. It really is worth thinking about
because you can't believe how many
doctors make the decisions based on, you
know, trusting uh these these outcomes.
So, here's the chart. what they looked
at from all of these um trials again
we've got 10,000 patients about 9600
patients with all seven trials and they
looked at um well what was the total
mortality uh the study pop in this study
they said you know what the relative
risk here was 1.05 05. That's 5%. And
they said, um, but it ranged. And did
they did they have a benefit for
lowering the
the blood pressure?
Um, you know, did they did they do
better? And you're trying to say, well,
this is a range from below the one where
it says no, they didn't do better, they
did worse to above the range. And then
they took the average, which was the
1.05. Okay. So the next one down was
these serious adverse effects. And
again, they said, well, the range of our
our confidence is it was below the one.
So that means it didn't make a
difference and that was uh right above
the one and you're like, "Oh, it did
make a difference." Real quick again,
usually when discussing risk, the lower
number is the better one. So the 0.94
would mean that the greater blood
pressure reduction reduces risk, not the
other way around. However, her main
point is spoton. Nothing seems to
indicate improvement with greater blood
pressure reduction. Is the high blood
pressure scam true? We'll find out
shortly. And then of course they give
you a 1.01. That's so mean. Um so total
cardiovascular deaths. Um they have
again a point8. The last one was okay.
So maybe maybe and again seven
randomized control trials. Um uh they do
grade themselves looking at several
things. I want to point out the two
moderate ones. Cardiovascular mortality
and total mortality. Deaths they do a
good job of. There's a good end point.
It's when you start getting wiggly on
what's a cardiovascular event, what's a
total uh um serious adverse event. Okay,
Dr. Boss briefly misspoke again in
relation to cardiovascular mortality and
events. Not a biggie. I do it too, but
I'm mentioning it because the
differences between those end points
matter. So, to be clear, let me pop open
the data for you. The lower blood
pressure had no effect on total
mortality, serious adverse events, and
cardiovascular mortality. We know that
because the estimated effect is close to
one and the confidence intervals clearly
overlap with the one. However, if you
look at the cardiovascular events which
is heart attacks, stroke, sudden death
and hospitalization or death from heart
failure, the confidence intervals barely
touch one. This is very important. Keep
that in mind because I'll be explaining
the significance of this in a bit. Also,
one more quick reminder. The certainty
of evidence that Dr. Bos describes is
the certainty of the quality of the
evidence based on the potential bias
that we discussed earlier. It doesn't
speak to the certainty of the end points
like death. You can have a low certainty
of evidence of death and a higher
certainty of cardiovascular events for
example. But let's get to the punchline,
the conclusions Dr. Bos makes off these
data and then I'd like to bring your
attention to a few things. What did
these smartypy pants and the Cochran
Library say in the end? They said the
evidence of all these seven trials
include the blood pressures that uh were
more frequently achieved in the standard
blood pressure group than in the lower.
Okay, that's pretty easy to think about.
When you're trying to lower the blood
pressure even further, it was easier to
get to the to the ones that weren't as
strict than the than the lower ones. And
they used a bunch more prescription
medications to get there. What they did
uh want to what I want to point out is
they detected no benefit for total
mortality or cardiovascular mortality.
And those are the two places where they
have they had confidence. Moderate to
high confidence that we all don't think
you should be pushing blood pressure
that low. If you do you're doing it for
reasons that were not quite like you
here's some there's a downside. Did you
see the downside? Hey, I'm getting to
it. Um we also found no difference uh
with regards to the total cardiovascular
events meaning heart attacks, m strokes,
sudden death, hospitalization and death
from heart failure. And the the total
serious adverse events uh were also they
found no difference. Most withdrawals
were due to the adverse events occurring
in the lower targeted group. Uh meaning
you were more likely to withdraw when
they were pushing your blood pressure
lower. And that's where they had the
lower confidence in this. Uh that's
where the lowest confidence was in
there. But uh it is not to to be um um
um uh that that's not to be ignored.
That that's actually really important
part of when you're looking at the sum
total of what we're trying to do with
lowering that blood pressure. The
patient's coming to the doctor saying,
"Hey doc, I know blood pressure is a big
deal. what number should I get to? And
they're trying to, you know, they're
trying to help you in a healthy
relationship. The patient's going to
help you get the outcomes that you're
telling them to get to. And what we're
saying is, I can push like hell. I have
two really good examples from this
morning's pinchasers that I'm going to
use to drive home the point. Well, what
is the punch line? What would I do now?
We can see that with these the this
review again coming out in 2022.
This is a few years old, and I'm I'm a
little embarrassed that it took me this
long to find um to get to what um to
really slow down and review this
information. Um, but I'm also like I
follow a few smarty pants people that
are influencers and hardly anybody
talked about this Cochran review. This
is an incredible review that says, "Do
you really need to push blood pressure
down that low? Am I really helping
them?" Because there are some adverse
events when I push them down too far.
And if I'm doing that in the name of
stopping a heart attack, well, for
heaven's sakes, I'm going to show you
how to do that. We're going to figure
out how to prevent those adverse events.
But if you're telling me we didn't stop
any we didn't stop any deaths from heart
attacks, we didn't stop any overall
deaths in these patients and we we
really didn't change the morbid, you
know, their the quality of life unless
you're counting adverse events from
lowering their blood pressure too much.
And then we started to say, well, the
net gain is you're hurting the more
patients and you're helping. Okay, first
off, in defense of Dr. Bos, not knowing
about an analysis isn't anything to be
embarrassed about. There's so much
research out there, it's unrealistic to
think that you'll be up to date on
everything all the time. Now, to her
points, I'd like to address her first
point last because it's a vital piece of
information that's being glossed over.
So, to address the other points, yes, it
took more medications to achieve the
lower blood pressure target. And even
though there was this lower blood
pressure target, no mortality measures
total or cardiovascular specific
indicated a benefit. That's all true.
That's what the Cochran analysis
indicates. No debating it. Okay. Now, I
held back this entire time, but now it's
time to contextualize these results
appropriately. One, the first point,
more people hit their blood pressure
targets in the standard treatment than
in the intensive treatment. On the other
hand, it might indicate it's more
difficult to take multiple drugs and
there might be side effects that led to
more withdrawals from the study. That's
a critique of using multiple blood
pressure medications, for example.
However, what else does this tell us? It
tells us that the people who took the
medication more often were the people in
the standard treatment condition. So
what do you think happens to the results
when one group takes their medication
and achieves the target blood pressure
more than the other? Right? That group
will have an outsized advantage. Only
about 64% of those in the intensive
treatment achieved the target blood
pressure. On top of that, one critique
that the researchers mentioned is that
the difference between the two groups
was only set to five units. Remember it
was 140 over 90 and 135 over 85. So the
overall amount of difference is small
although still clinically relevant and
beneficial. Now there are three primary
levers that researchers can use to
determine if something is effective or
not especially when it comes to diseases
that take decades to present. Yet you
only have a limited number of years with
which to run the trial. The three
primary levers are one, time, the length
of the trial. The longer that you extend
it, the closer you get to the actual
lifetime exposure of the disease. Number
two, the effect size, the magnitude of
the effect, as we discussed. If the
effect difference is small, you'll need
to use the other two levers to detect a
difference. If the effect is large,
which is more true for shorter disease
progressions, this lever can be pretty
powerful. Three, the sample size. The
number of participants in the study. If
you increase the sample size, the other
two levers can be diminished somewhat
and you can detect an effect if there is
one. Okay, so this analysis included
seven studies, which means over 9,000
participants. Seems like a lot. However,
keep in mind that cardiovascular disease
is a disease of decades. Yet, these
studies lasted an average of about 3.5
years. Now, keep in mind that the effect
size was relatively modest. In fact, the
researchers addressed that last point by
doing a subgroup analysis here where
they only included studies that had at
least 10 point difference in blood
pressure. I love the idea, but they've
paid one lever by robbing another. Look
at the sample size now. It's less than
30% of what it was originally. To be
clear, they found the same effect, or
should I say a lack of an effect as the
main analysis. Okay. So, why does any of
this matter? It only matters if there's
a chance that we're missing an effect
that might actually be present itself.
If we have more or better data, here's
the thing. We have some evidence of that
being the case. Remember this. Remember
the cardiovascular events were extremely
close to being statistically
significant. In fact, if you look at the
forest plot, even the statistics as
reported indicate an effect as the p
value is
0.05. I'll bet this was reported as not
statistically significant because there
might be some other numbers uh that are
after the five that are cut off or it
needed to be 1/100th under 0.05. 05. So,
do we now make groundbreaking
conclusions off data that barely misses
statistical significance by a hair?
Well, don't take my word for it. Even
the researchers state, "We cannot state
these results are conclusive and then
later mention multiple other studies are
in the works to fill in some of the data
for this analysis. Kindly, they supplied
all the study names." So, I did a bit of
soouththing and here they are with their
updated results as of early 2025. Three
trials are ongoing even now. Two trials
I couldn't find. One study indicated no
effect of further blood pressure
reduction and two trials showed
improvements in cardiovascular events
with greater blood pressure reduction.
Now, this is speculation, but if we were
to input the three trials that we have
now, it seems likely to me that we'd
reach statistical significance in the
cardiovascular events outcome,
indicating further blood pressure
reduction is beneficial for reducing
cardiovascular events like heart attacks
and strokes in people with
cardiovascular disease. But that still
leaves one outstanding question.
Assuming that we see improvements in
cardiovascular disease events, why don't
we see that reflected in mortality end
points? Well, if you'll give me a bit
more time, I'll explain that, too. But
there's also more to say, and this video
is way longer than I wanted it to be.
Yet, I have more to say than that. So,
I'm leaving the rest for, believe it or
not, the extended version of this video,
included for the Physionic Insiders,
along with all of my analyses, a private
library of videos, articles, podcasts,
live sessions with me to ask questions,
and much more. You can access that by
joining the Physionic Insiders in the
description box of this video. I hope to
see you there. And I'd be shocked if
someone wanted even more of this kind of
deep dive, but it's there if you want
it. I'll see you there. Now, why a
potential difference in cardiovascular
events, but not mortality? Well, the
answer is actually really simple. Death
is a great endpoint, except for those
involved, but it also has a higher
threshold to achieve. That means if a
person has a heart attack, they might
not die. Which means many more people
have heart attacks than die, which
reduces the amount of data input for the
mortality data, thereby reducing the
power of the analysis. So the correct
interpretation is exactly what Dr. Boss
said. There's no effect of further
lowering blood pressure, but we
shouldn't jump to the conclusion that
may not change in the future. It's
likely a reason the researchers said
this analysis, while robust, is not
conclusive. Okay, then enough babbling.
I'll leave the rest for my extended
video for the insiders. What's the
takeaway here? The takeaway is that this
analysis does indicate different results
from the sprint trial, which means
lowering blood pressure beyond 140 units
over 90 units if you have cardiovascular
disease is not warranted to prevent
mortality or even events by the
strictest letter of the analysis.
However, and a big however, I think and
the researchers acknowledge there's more
data that's needed to make a definitive
statement. So, opting for lower blood
pressure, especially through
non-farmaceutical means, is likely the
more prudent way to go right now. There
is a lot of wiggle room for things to
change. If you're interested in a more
detailed look at blood pressure and this
sprint trial, check out this video. and
otherwise I explain nonfarma ways of
reducing blood pressure right here too.
Thanks for hanging out with me.
[Music]